{
  "title": "Data_Structure - Data_Structure — Slot 19 (18 Questions)",
  "duration": 50,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Data_Structure — Slot 19",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following statements:<br><br>\n(i). First-in-first out types of computations are efficiently supported by STACKS. <br>\n(ii). Implementing LISTS on linked lists is more efficient than implementing LISTS on an array for almost all the basic LIST operations.<br>\n(iii). Implementing QUEUES on a circular array is more efficient than implementing QUEUES on a linear array with two indices.<br>\n(iv). Last-in-first-out type of computations are efficiently supported by QUEUES. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(ii) and (iii) are true</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(i) and (ii) are true</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(iii) and (iv) are true</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(ii) and (iv) are true</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>(ii) and (iii) are true</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2716/gate1996-1-12\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following statements is true?<br>\nI. As the number of entries in a hash table increases, the number of collisions increases.<br>\nII. Recursive programs are efficient<br>\nIII. The worst case complexity for Quicksort is \\(O(n^2)\\)<br>\nIV. Binary search using a linear linked list is efficient<br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I and II</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II and III</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I and IV</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I and III</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>I and III</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2634/gate1995-2-22\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The postfix expression for the infix expression A+B*(C+D)/F+D*E is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>AB + CD + *F/D +E*</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>ABCD + *F/DE* ++</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>A * B + CD/F *DE ++</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>A + *BCD/F* DE ++</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>ABCD + *F/DE* ++</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2633/gate1995-2-21\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>A binary tree T has n leaf nodes. The number of nodes of degree 2 in T is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\log_2 n\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>n-1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>n</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2^n\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>n-1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2604/gate1995-1-17\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>For merging two sorted lists of sizes \\(m\\) and \\(n\\) into a sorted list of size \\(m+n\\), we require comparisons of <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O(m)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O(n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O(m+n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(\\log m + \\log n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O(m+n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2603/gate1995-1-16\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following statements is false? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1994)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Optimal binary search tree construction can be performed efficiently using dynamic programming</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Breadth-first search cannot be used to find connected components of a graph</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Given the prefix and postfix walks over a binary tree, the binary tree cannot be uniquely constructed.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Depth-first search can be used to find connected components of a graph</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Breadth-first search cannot be used to find connected components of a graph</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2465/gate1994-1-22\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Linked lists are not suitable data structures for which one of the following problems? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1994)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Insertion sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Binary search</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Radix sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Polynomial manipulation</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Binary search</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2460/gate1994-1-17-ugcnet-sep2013-ii-32\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following permutations can be obtained in the output (in the same order) using a stack assuming that the input is the sequence 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 in that order? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1994)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>3, 4, 5, 1, 2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>3, 4, 5, 2, 1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1, 5, 2, 3, 4</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>5, 4, 3, 1, 2</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>3, 4, 5, 2, 1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2457/gate1994-1-14\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>In a compact single dimensional array representation for lower triangular matrices (i.e all the elements above the diagonal are zero) of size \\(n \\times n\\), non-zero elements, (i.e elements of lower triangle) of each row are stored one after another, starting from the first row, the index of the \\((i, j)^{th}\\) element of the lower triangular matrix in this new representation is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1994)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(i+j\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(i+j-1\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\((j-1)+\\frac{i(i-1)}{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(i+\\frac{j(j-1)}{2}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\((j-1)+\\frac{i(i-1)}{2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2452/gate1994-1-11\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>What is the minimum number of stacks of size n required to implement a queue\nto size n ? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2001)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>One</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>two</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>three</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>four</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>two</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/734/gate2001-2-16#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Consider any array representation of an n element binary heap where the elements\nare stored from index 1 to index n of the array. For the element stored at index\ni of the array (\\(i\\leq n\\) ) , the index of the parent is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2001)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>i-1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left \\lfloor \\frac{i}{2} \\right \\rfloor\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{i}{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{(i+1)}{2}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left \\lfloor \\frac{i}{2} \\right \\rfloor\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/708/gate2001-1-15#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (more than one may be correct) and write the corresponding letters only:<br><br>\nA 2-3 tree is such that<br>\na. All internal nodes have either 2 or 3 children<br>\nb. All paths from root to the leaves have the same length.<br><br>The number of internal nodes of a 2-3 tree having 9 leaves could be <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1992)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>6</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>7</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>4</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/562/gate1992-02-vii\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (more than one may be correct) and write the corresponding letters only:\n<br>The following sequence of operations is performed on a stack:<br>\nPUSH  (10), PUSH (20), POP, PUSH (10), PUSH (20), POP, POP, POP, PUSH (20), POP<br>\nThe sequence of values popped out is<br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1991)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>20,10,20,10,20</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>20,20,10,10,20</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>10,20,20,10,20</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>20,20,10,20,10</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>20,20,10,10,20</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/522/gate1991-03-vii\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (More than one may be correct).<br>The total external path length, EPL, of a binary tree with n external nodes is, \\(\\Sigma _w=Iw\\), where \\(I_{w}\\) is the path length of external node w), <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1990)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\leq n^{2}\\) always.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\geq n \\log_{2}\\) n always.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Equal to \\(n^{2}\\) always.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>O(n) for some special trees.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\geq n \\log_{2}\\) n always.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/84828/gate1990-3-iv\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (More than one may be correct).<br>The number of rooted binary trees with n nodes is, <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1990)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Equal to the number of ways of multiplying (n+1) matrices.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Equal to the number of ways of arranging n out of 2 n distinct elements.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Equal to \\(\\frac{1}{(n+1)}\\binom{2n}{n}\\).</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Equal to n!.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Equal to the number of ways of multiplying (n+1) matrices.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/84060/gate1990-3-iii\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 16,
          "question": "<p>Answer the following:<br>Which one of the following statements (s) is/are FALSE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1989)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Overlaying is used to run a program, which is longer than the address space of the computer.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Optimal binary search tree construction can be performed efficiently by using dynamic programming.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Depth first search cannot be used to find connected components of a graph.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Given the prefix and postfix walls over a binary tree, the binary tree can be uniquely constructed.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Overlaying is used to run a program, which is longer than the address space of the computer.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/87143/gate1989-3-ixa\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 17,
          "question": "<p>A hash table with ten buckets with one slot per bucket is shown in the following figure. The symbols S1 to S7 initially entered using a hashing function with linear probing. The maximum number of comparisons needed in searching an item that is not present is<br>\\(\\begin{array}{|l|l|} \\hline 0 &amp; \\text { S7 } \\\\ \\hline 1 &amp; \\text { S1 } \\\\ \\hline 2 &amp; \\\\ \\hline 3 &amp; \\text { S4 } \\\\ \\hline 4 &amp; \\text { S2 } \\\\ \\hline 5 &amp; \\text { } \\\\ \\hline 6 &amp; \\text { S5 } \\\\ \\hline 7 &amp; \\\\ \\hline 8 &amp; \\text { S6 } \\\\ \\hline 9 &amp; \\text { S3 } \\\\ \\hline \\end{array}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1989)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>6</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>3</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>5</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/10905/gate1989-1-vii-isro2015-14\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 18,
          "question": "<p>In a circular linked list oraganisation, insertion of a record involves modification of <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1987)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>One pointer.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Two pointers.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Multiple pointers.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>No pointer.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Two pointers.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/80298/gate1987-1-xv\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}